

data journalism & storytelling · consultancy & research · training & workshops

I'm a freelance data journalist and data-driven storyteller. I counsel NGOs, non-profits and businesses on researching and producing data-driven stories. I give talks, trainings and workshops on data-driven storytelling techniques and best practices. I'm available to carry out academic and journalistic research. I was lead data journalist and trainer at Silk.co, a semantic web platform for publishing and visualizing data. Before, I've crafted data journalism stories and data visualizations for digital and print Italian news outlets. I privilege the use of open source tools and/or of coding. I have a background in History and a MA specializing in data journalism. I'm Italian, currently based in Amsterdam (NL).



DATA JOURNALISM & STORYTELLING

I have both an academic background and several years of work experience in crafting data journalism pieces and producing data driven storytelling, with a focus on advocacy. I am comfortable with different parts of the workflow, from scraping to visualizations



CONSULTANCY & RESEARCH

Whether you have a story that needs data, data that needs a story, or an idea that needs both, I offer consultancy and research assistance to organizations interested in integrating data in their workflows and reporting.



TRAINING & WORKSHOP

I give workshop sessions and full training courses on data journalism and data driven storytelling techniques, covering topics like data sourcing and scraping, data cleaning, data analysis for journalists, data visualization and storytelling.

SKILLS

RESEARCH	Using multiple methodologies (content analysis of texts & digital entities; research interview; survey); finding data for stories, how to access it & how to complement it
DATA SCRAPING	Getting the data in a machine-readable format. Python, APIs, XPath scraping in Google Sheets
DATA WRANGLING	Cleaning and restructuring of messy data. OpenRefine + GREL expressions, Python, RegEx
DATA ANALYSIS	Exploratory + statistical analysis. Google Sheets/Excel, Python
DATA STORYTELLING	Putting together insights to form a story; presenting the story; finding possible gaps and limitations
DATA VISUALIZATION	Networks visualizations, maps, timelines, (interactive) charts, infographics

WORK EXPERIENCE

DATA-DRIVEN STORYTELLING CONSULTANT & RESEARCHER

Aug. 2016 - Present

@ Freelancer

- Assisting clients (NGOs, academia and journalists) with data driven stories/research
- Trainer at international and local events (see events section of my website for list)

LEAD DATA JOURNALIST & TRAINER

Jan. 2014 - Aug. 2016

@ Silk.co

The startup behind the semantic platform for data publishing and interactive storytelling. Successfully acquired by Palantir in Aug. 2016.

- Hired to boost Silk's content marketing strategy.
- Creator of viral stories that generate traffic and visibility on social media and international news outlets.
- Projects featured in <u>The Guardian</u>, <u>Information is Beautiful</u>, <u>Vox</u>, <u>CNN</u>, <u>The Atlantic</u> and others
- Trainer at international and local events (see events section of my website for list))

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Sept. 2013 - Jan. 2014

@ DataJLab

A virtual lab at Tilburg University on data journalism trends and techniques

- Member of the "Climate Finance Lab" team, investigating financial data stories behind climate policies.
- Co-authored paper with Dr. Stefania Milan on journalism & algorithms. Selected for a panel at "Rethinking Journalism"

JOURNALIST

May 2013 - Jan. 2014

@ Freelancer

• Published data-driven pieces for print and digital Italian outlets. Clients include Wired Italy and datajournalism.it

JOURNALIST TRAINEE

April 2013 - June 2013

@ NRC next

Major Dutch newspaper.

• Internship that led to data-driven investigative journalism piece on Interpol

EDUCATION

POST-GRADUATE LEARNING

- Winter University: Using European data for better storytelling by European People's Party · Brussels, Belgium
- Shift, Shape, Mobilize Workshop by Sourcefabric and n-ost · Odessa, Ukraine
- Won scholarship for the Summer School for Journalists and Media Practitioners @ European University Institute · Fiesole, Italy
- Data4Change by SmallMedia and VisualizingImpact· Beirut, Lebanon
- Young European Journalist Workshop "Data and Journalism: Between big stories and dirty surveillance" · Potsdam, Germany
- Data Journalism Workshop "Turning Data into Stories" by MediaLab Prado · Madrid, Spain
- School of Data Journalism, workshops by School of Data · Perugia, Italy
- See the "Events" section of my website for others

COMMUNICATION & INFORMATION SCIENCES (MA) · DATA JOURNALISM

August 2012 - August 2013

@University of Tilburg (The Netherlands)

- Graduated with distinction
- Thesis "Social meets civic: Civic social media and open government data: An inquiry on collaborative fact-checking for citizens' empowerment"
- One of the two students chosen for a data journalism internship at NRC Next (major Dutch newspaper)

HISTORY, TRADITION AND INNOVATION (BA)

September 2008 - July 2012

@University of Siena (Italy)

- Graduated cum laude
- Thesis analyzing media discourse in Italian newspapers during the 2011 war in Libya and NATO's intervention
- Specialized in the period from the 1789 French Revolution to current days. Elective courses in Philosophy, Human Rights, Economic History and Globalization

MORE IN DEPHT

- You can view a portfolio of my projects at alice-corona.nl/portfolio
- You can read a list of training and workshops I've followed or given at alice-corona.nl/events
- You can have a look at a few tutorials I've written up at alice-corona.nl/tutorials

GET IN TOUCH

alice-corona.nl alice-corona@riseup.net +31 6 333 56867

FOLLOW

medium.com/@alice_corona

witter.com/alice_corona

github.com/ali-ce